Good morning.
My name is Karl Anderson.
I'm one of the medical demonstrators here.
Could I just check your name and your date of birth, please?
Yeah, it's Kalam Smith, 10th of December 1999.
Okay, and what would you like me to call you today?
Kalam's fine.
Kalam, okay.
So, Kalam, what I would like to do today is perform an eye examination.
What this will involve me doing is coming quite close and shining a bright light into your eyes.
eyes.
It might be a little bit uncomfortable but it shouldn't be painful.
Does that sound
okay with you?
Yeah, that's fine.
Okay, so to start off with I'm just going to have a quick
look at your eyes.
Comment on the appearance of the eyes, the height of the eyelids, the
shape and size of the pupils, any proptosis and for signs of redness, swelling or discharge.
Move on to use the traditional Ophthalmoscope or Arc Light to view the back
of the eye.
The arc light has a side tool at the top of the device, a
grey on-off switch which also
allows toggling through the different light settings and a range of lenses.
In most situations it is best to use the arc light with a rack
of lenses set at the top.
In this position there is no lens but instead just a clear hole.
In a traditional direct-off thermoscope there is also a side hole at the top,
a colour to
turn the light on and off as well as to adjust the brightness and
a rack of lenses.
The lenses in an enough thermoscope can neutralise both the examiners and patients for active
errors.
This can help to see the retina more clearly.
In the first instance however we recommend
setting the lens power and the ophthalmoscope to zero and for the examiner and patient to
both wear their usual optical correction, either glasses or contact lenses.
If the back
of the eye cannot be seen clearly then remove the patient's spectacles and use the lenses
of the device instead.
Try both options to see what you prefer.
It is always easier to see the back of the eye clearly if the pupils are dilated.
If
you cannot dilate the pupils then examine in a dimly lit room.
Also, when performing fundoscopy in a patient with an undilated pupil,
set the ophthalmoscope to a low or medium brightness.
This will reduce how much the
pupil constricts, also helping you see the back of the eye more easily.
I'm just going to shine the light so if you look directly into the
light for me.
To assess the red reflex use the brightest light setting on the ophthalmoscope.
Either turn the collar on the traditional device or press the gray button on the
the arc light until the brightest light is selected.
Select the zero lens of the direct
off-tharmoscope or the top position on the lens rack of the arc light.
In this position
the sight hole of the arc light has no lens at all, it is just a hole.
Examine in a room
with dim lighting or in the dark to gain the best view.
Hold the off-tharmoscope in your
dominant hand at arm's length from the patient.
Ask the patient to look at the light and
observe both eyes at the same time comparing the appearance of light reflecting back through
pupils.
Comment on the colour of the reflected light relative brightness or absence of reflected
light.
This video demonstrates loss of the red reflex in the right eye due to a dense mature
cataract.
This examination shows early cortical cataract in the right eye and in this patient
a dense central dark opacity due to the congenital posterior polar cataract is seen.
Not all red
reflex abnormalities are due to cataract, and this exam a dense scar of the
cornea due to
previous infection was the main cause.
And if I can now get you to focus on the light switch behind me.
Next move on to look at the back of the eye.
Hold the ophthalmoscope in your right hand to examine
the right eye and vice versa.
Start with your feet close to the patient and lean back.
Ask the
patient to fix on a specific distance target on the horizontal and avoid looking
at the light of
of the ophthalmoscope.
Slowly start to move in from 10 to 15 degrees temporal on the horizontal
meridian with the zero power lens.
Keep the red reflex in view and move closer to the patient.
The optic disc should come into view when you're a few centimeters away.
Comment on how distinctive
the margin of the disc is, the colour of the neuro-retinal rim and cup
to disc ratio.
If you cannot see the disc then move in the direction that the branches
of the retinal vessel
point.
This will guide you towards the disc.
In this examination the optic nerve is swollen.
The margin is indistinct and the central cup is absent due to being filled
by the surrounding
swollen nerve.
The fine capillaries on the surface of the nerve are obscured as are some
of the large arterials.
The veins are swollen and there is a small hemorrhage present at
nine o'clock.
These signs are all consistent with
papaladema due to raised intracranial pressure.
This optic nerve has a much more distinct margin, but the neuro-retinal rim is diffusely pale.
This is the appearance of optic atrophy.
In this examination, the central cup is enlarged with thinning of the neuro-retinal rim.
The nerve consequently has an enlarged cup to disc ratio of 0.8, highly suggestive of the
presence of glaucoma.
Once you have seen and commented on the disc, follow the four major branches
of the retinal
vessels to look for other signs.
by asking the patient to look at the light.
This will bring the centre of the macula called
the fovea interview.
If the patient is not dilated as in this examination, the pupil will
constrict when shining light on the fovea, obscuring the view.
The examination of an eye with a dilated
pupil demonstrates a healthy fovea.
The fovea is a slightly darker central zone with a bright
pinpoint reflection on the centre.
Repeat this for the left eye and summarise your findings
for the examiner.
That's perfect.
Okay, thank you, Callum.
Thank you.
You'll be glad to hear
that was an entirely normal examination.
So thank you for coming in today.
Great, thanks.
Good morning.
My name is Carl Anderson.
I'm one of the medical demonstrators here.
Could
I just check your name and your date of birth please?
Yeah, so Callum Smith, 10th of December
in 1999.
Okay, and what would you like me to call you today?
Callum's fine.
Callum, okay.
what I would like to do today is perform an eye examination.
What this will involve me doing is
coming quite close and shining a bright light into your eyes.
It might be a little bit uncomfortable
but it shouldn't be painful.
Does that sound okay with you?
Yeah that's fine.
Okay so to start off
with I'm just going to have a quick look at your eyes.
I'm just going to shine the light so if you
looked directly into the light for me, that's perfect.
And if I can now get you to focus on the
light switch behind me and
if I can now get
you to look directly
at the light, that's perfect.
Okay, thank you, Callum.
Thank you.
You'll be glad to hear that was an entirely normal examination,
so thank you for coming in today.
Great, thanks.
Today I performed ophthalmoscopy on Callum Smith,
a 20-year-old male patient.
On initial inspection there was no obvious
tosses, redness or swelling of the eyelids and the eyes appeared straight with no obvious squint.
The pupils appeared round and symmetrical and the
conjunctiva, sclera and corneas were both healthy.
The red reflex was present bilaterally with equal
brightness in both eyes and there was
no evidence of opacities.
The margin, cup and colour of the optic discs was normal and there was
no evidence of disease
in the major blood vessels.
The retina and macula also appeared healthy.
In summary, this was a normal examination.